hello everyone today we are going to do
a problem based on Commerce surveying
let us read the question the following
four and back bearings were observed in
traversing with a canvas in place where
local attraction was suspected
find the corrected forbearing and back
bearing of lines using included angles
the lines are given for the lines the
four bearing and the back bearings are
given
Now using the four bearings we can draw
the Traverse
we know that these readings are given in
whole circle bearing
we know that the whole circle bearing of
your line is the horizontal angle
measured clockwise from the North Point
of the meridian
so all of the readings should be started
from the north
in this case in the north we will have
zero degree because it is the starting
point
in yeast we will have 90 degree in South
we will have 180 degree in West we will
have 270 degree anti again in the north
we will have 360 degree
so all of the readings are taken from
the north in the clockwise Direction
now let us start drawing the Traverse
first let us draw the Direction symbol
let us keep this station as a
the forbearing of a b is given as 158
degree 30 minutes
we know that here we have 0 degree here
90 and here 190 158 comes between 90 and
190 so in between we have to make a line
and then again we have to draw the
Direction symbol
this is the station B
the forbearing of BC is 62 degree
we know that here we have zero degree
here 90 degree
62 comes between 0 and 90. so we have to
draw a line between them
and then we have to make the Direction
symbol
the four bearing of C D is 342 degree we
know that here we have 0 degree here 90
here 190 here 270 and finally here 360
342 comes between 270 and 360. so in
between we have to make a line and then
we have to draw the Direction symbol
the forbearing of d e is given as 281
degree
here we have 270 degree and here 360
281 comes between 270 and
360. so we have to make a line in
between and then the Direction symbol
the forbearing of EA is a 210 degree 30
minutes here we have 190 and here we
have 270 degree we know that 210 comes
between 270 and 180 we have to make a
line between them and join the point a
now let us indicate the four bearings in
the Traverse
we know that all of the readings are
taken in the clockwise direction from
the north
now let us indicate the back bearings
back bearing is the reverse of
forbearing
back bearing of a b is ba
back bearing of BCE c b
it is DC it is e d and it is a e
B to a is 339 degree
c2b is a 242 degree
d2c is 163 degree
e2d is 101 degree 30 minutes
and finally a e is 30 degree
now we can check the back B Rings
whether our drawing is correct
for example let us take this angle 30
degree
here we have 0 degree and here we have
90 degree 30 degree comes between 0 and
90 so the drawing is correct
let us take this angle 339 degree
here we have 270 and here we have 360
339 comes in between them so our drawing
is correct
in the similar way we can check this
angle this angle and this angle all of
them are correct
now we are going to find the included
angles
the Traverse is running in the
anti-clockwise direction
so the included angles will be the
interior angles
we know that the interior angles or
these angles
first let us find the interior angle a
to find this angle we have to subtract
this angle by this angle when we do that
we are getting 128 degree 30 minutes
now let us find the interior angle B
let us split this angle into two parts
right side and left side right side we
have 62 degree
in the left side we do not know how much
we know that one circle is 360 degree to
find this angle we have to subtract 339
by 360 degree
so this angle is 360 minus 339 when we
add the left side and right side we will
get the interior angle B
now let us find the interior angle C
we can easily find this angle by
subtracting this angle by this angle
when we do that we are getting 100
degree
let us find the interior angle d
we can easily find this angle by
subtracting this angle by this angle
when we do that we are getting 1 180
degree
finally let us find the interior angle e
this angle also can be easily found by
subtracting this angle by this angle
when we do that we are getting 1.9
degree
so it is very easy to find these four
interior angles
only in the station B it was a little
difficult
now let us find the sum of the observed
angles for that we have to add these
five angles
when we add we will get this angle
now let us find the theoretical sum of
the angles the formula is 2 N minus 4
into 9 t
n is the number of stations here we have
1 2 3 4 5 stations
so n is 5 2 into 5 minus 4 we will get 6
6 into 90 we will get 540 degree
the error is 538 degree 30 minutes minus
540 degree we will get negative 1 degree
30 minutes
since the error is negative the
correction should be positive
we know that we have totally five
stations
to find the correction for each station
we have to divide these by the number of
stations which is 5 when we do that we
will get positive 18 minutes
now let us find the corrected interior
angles for that with these angles we
have to add 18 minutes
when we do that we will get to these
angles
now we can verify our answers again we
have to add all of these angles
we will get 540 degree
we have found all of the included angles
Now using these angles we can find the
corrected four bearings and back
bearings
we know that the difference between four
bearing and back bearing should be 190
degree
in a b c d d e and e a the difference of
back bearing and forbearing will not be
198 degree only in BC the difference
will be 180 degree
so these two readings are correct
this is forbearing of BC let us enter
that this is a back bearing of BC let us
enter that also
we know that both of these two bearings
are correct using them we can find the
other corrected bearings
using 62 degree we can go this way and
find the corrected bearings
or using 242 degree we can go this way
and find the corrected bearings
I am going to use 242 degree and go this
way and find the corrected bearings
Now using this angle we can find a
bearing of CD
in the station C we know the interior
angle hundred degree 18 minutes
to find the bearing of CED we have to
add these two angles
when we add we will get 342 degree 18
minutes
we know that this is the forbearing of
CED using that we can find the back
bearing of CD which is DC
the formula to find the back bearing is
forbearing plus or minus 180 degree
we have to use the positive sign when
the forbearing is less than 180 we have
to use the negative sign when the
forbearing is more than 180
here the four bearing is more than 180
degree so we have to use the negative
sign
finally for the bearing of DC we will
get 162 degree 18 minutes
let us enter that
now let us find the forbearing of d e to
find this angle we have to add these two
angles
when we add we will get 280 degree 36
minutes
let us enter that
Now using these four bearing we can find
the back bearing Ed
it is more than 180 so we have to use
the negative sign
for the bearing of e d we will get 100 a
degree 36 minutes
let us enter that
now let us find the bearing of EA for
that we have to add these two angles
when we add we will get 2.9 degree 54
minutes
Now using these four bearing we can find
the back bearing AE
since it is more than 180 degree we have
to use the negative sign
for the bearing of eae we will get 29
degree 54 minutes
now let us find the forbearing of a B
for that we have to add these two angles
when we add we will get 158 degree 42
minutes
Now using these four bearing we can find
this back bearing
since this angle is less than 180 degree
we have to use the positive sign
finally for the bearing of ba we will
get 338 degree 42 minutes
Now using these two angles we can find
the four bearing of b c
to get this angle we have to subtract
this angle by this angle
we know that one circle is a 360 degree
360 degree minus this angle 338 degree
42 minutes
we will get this angle
so this angle minus this angle we will
get bearing of BC which is 62 degree we
already know it is a 62 degree so this
calculation can be made as a check
since we have got the correct value our
calculations are correct
here I have entered all of the corrected
bearings
now for all of the lines the difference
between four bearing and back bearing
will be 180 degree
now we are going to end this session
thank you for watching this video